hello大家好我是凯超
Hello everyone, I am Kaichao
我们今天课程内容是substrate runtime
The content of our course today is Substrate Runtime
数据存储的设计
Data Storage Design
本次课程内容主要包括了
This course mainly includes
区块链存储和传统互联网应用的存储
Blockchain storage and storage of traditional Internet applications
不同点和约束
Differences and constraints between them
以及substrate
and substrate
所提供的存储单元的数据类型
of the provided storage unit by Substrate
知识的有哪些
Which types are supported
接着我们会介绍如何使用
Then we'll show you how to use
substrate的存储单元
Substrate storage unit
进行一个创始区块的初始化
to initialize a genesis block
最后我们会介绍一下使用substrate进行
Finally, we will introduce the use of substrate for
存储设计的时候一些最佳实践
some best practices in storage design
大家知道
Everybody knows
区块链通常有这样几个特点
Blockchain usually has the following characteristics
第一个是它的代码是完全开源的
The first is that its code is completely open source
可以供所有人去审查
It is available for everyone to review
并且它是由对等网络组成的
and it is made up of a peer-to-peer network
这样一个区中心的网络
such a decentralized network.
那通过引入了延迟和随机来在
That introduces delay and randomness to
不同的节点之间达成共识
achieve consensus  between different nodes
那在这样的一个网络环境里面
Then in such a network environment
区块链使用了
Blockchain
链式的增量的形式来存储数据
stores data in the form of chained incremental manner.
区块之间彼此是通过链式直接连接
Blocks are directly connected to each other through chains
并且所有的节点都会备份
and all nodes will be backed up
链上的状态数据
state data on the chain.
有一些Archive的节点
There are some Archive nodes
甚至会保存所有的历史数据
even save all historical data
这就对
That needs that
节点的存储和性能都有比较高的要求
the node storage and performance have relatively high requirements
区块链应用的程序
Programs for blockchain applications
它通常都会有高效的键值对数据库
It usually has an efficient key-value pair database
比如bitcoin里面使用的LevelDB
For example, LevelDB used in bitcoin
以太坊及Substrate里面使用的RocksDB
RocksDB used in Ethereum and Substrate
当我们在使用区块链作为我们
When we are using blockchain as our
Web 3.0业务的载体的时候
carrier of Web 3.0 business
它的存储有这些限制
Its storage has these limitations
第一个是
the first is
大文件如果直接存储在链
If large files are stored directly in the chain
上的成本是非常高的
The cost is very high.
通常情况下我们需要选择一种
Usually we need to choose a
中心化的或者去中心的
centralized or decentralized
存储形式来存储
storage form to store
大的文件
large files
而只是在链上存储一个很小的
Instead, just store a small
文件的哈希值
file hash on the chain.
我们刚才已经提到了
we just mentioned
链式的区块存储结构
chained block storage structure
那这种结构
that structure
其实并不利于对历史数据的索引
In fact, it is not conducive to the indexing of historical data
因为你如果想索引的话
because if you want to index
你就需要
you have to
遍历当前区块往前所有的区块
traverse all blocks before the current block
那这就要求我们通常会有一个
Then this requires that we usually have a
链下的这样的一个索引的服务
such an off-chain index service
通常也就是我们的
Usually
区块浏览器这样的一个基础设施
It's an infrastructure such as a block explorer
另外一个约束是
Another constraint is
由于区块链的逻辑
that due to the logic of the blockchain
是在不同的节点之间
between different nodes
都要去运行这样的一个逻辑
has to be ran
要求逻辑执行的结果必须是完全
It is required that the result of logic execution must be completely
一致的
consistent.
那浮点数的话
For the floating point number
它的运算结果跟编译器以及
Its result has direct relationship with
CPU的架构都有直接的关系
the compiler and the architecture of the CPU.
所以我们在区块链里面是不能使用
So we cannot use float numbers
浮点数的
in the blockchain
而是需要使用其他
Instead, you need to use other
固定点的小数来模拟浮点数
fixed-point decimals to simulate
这样的一个操作
floating-point numbers.
我们之前在课程中已经简单提到过
We've briefly mentioned this earlier in the course
嗯substrate链上的存储单元
Well, the storage unit on the substrate chain
有单值类型StorageValue
There is a single value type StorageValue
简单映射类型StorageMap
Simple mapping type StorageMap
以及双键映射类型
and the double keys mapping type
StorageDoubleMap
以及多键映射类型StorageNMAP
and the multi-key mapping type StorageNMAP
那在开发链上的存储单元的时候
When developing storage units on the chain
有这些点需要去注意
There are these points to pay attention to
substrate支持了一些Rust的原生数据类型
substrate supports some of Rust's native data types
它是
it is
Rust的所有原生数据类型的一个子集
a subset of all of Rust's native data types.
那这些子集是定义在Rust的核心库和
Those subsets are defined in the Rust core library and
Alloc库之中
In the Alloc library
进一步substrate支持的这样的原生类型
Such native types supported by Substrate
可以构成我们刚刚提到的
can constitute what we just mentioned
映射类型
mapping type
其实substrate支持的这些原生类型
In fact, these native types supported by Substrate
就是对
is for that
这些原生类型实现了一定的编解码的
these native types implement a certain codec
规则
rule
我们现在来回顾一下
let's review now
上节课所了解到的storage宏
the storage macro learned in the last lesson.
我们定义了一个something这样一个storage
We define a storage like something
那它的类型是StorageValue
Then its type is StorageValue
存储的值是一个32位无符号的整数
The stored value is a 32-bit unsigned integer
我们是使用的pallet::storage这个宏
We are using the pallet::storage macro
并且我们有一个可选的getter函数
and we have an optional getter function
名字叫做something
the name is something
除了我们刚才看到的32位
In addition to the 32-bit we just saw
无符号整数这样的一个单质类型
A primitive type such as unsigned integers
其实还有其他各种各样的单值类型
In fact, there are various other single value types
那单值类型其实顾名思义就是
The single-value type, as the name implies, is
只能用来存储某一种单一类型的值
can only be used to store a single type of value
比如它是布尔值数值类型
For example it is a boolean numeric type
或者枚举或者结构体
or enumeration or structure
数值类型有8位
Numeric types have 8 bits
无符号有符号整数以及32位64位
unsigned signed integer and 32-bit 64-bit
128位等等
128 bits etc.
还有一些Substrate内置的大整数类型有256
There are also some built-in large integer types in Substrate with 256
有512等等
There are 512 and so on
布尔类型以及集合类型有vector
Boolean types and collection types have vector
BTreeMap和BTreeSet
BTreeMap and BTreeSet
我们刚才提到了
we just mentioned
区块链不能直接使用浮点数
Blockchain cannot directly use floating point numbers
那么取而代之的是定点小数
Then instead of fixed-point decimals
Substrate内置的有
Substrate has built-in
Percent, Permil, Perbill以及FixedU128
Percent, Permil, Perbill and FixedU128
还有一些自定义的类型
There are also some custom types
比如定常的哈西H128H256
For example, the regular Hash H128H256
可以快速方便的去表示哈西的结果
It can quickly and conveniently express the result of Hash
Substrate支持的其他的一些复杂类型
Some other complex types supported by Substrate
包括了Option
include Option
这样的一个有值或者无值
such a value or no value
这样的一个类型
such a type
Tuple元组
Tuple
它可以包含多个元素
it can contain multiple elements
这些不同的元素
these different elements
的类型可以是不一样的
Their types can be different
以及枚举
and enumeration
以及结构体可以包含更多的属性信息
And the structure can contain more attribute information
还有一些特定的内置自定义类型
There are also some specific built-in custom types
比如Timestamp
Such as Timestamp
模块会定义的Moment
Moment defined by the module
来表示我们当前区块的时间戳
to represent the timestamp of our current block
以及系统模块提供的AccountId表示
and the AccountId provided by the system module represents
用户的account标识
user's account ID
通常情况下它是用户私钥所对应的
Usually it is the user's private key corresponding to
公钥信息
the public key information
我们先来看一下数值类型
Let's take a look at the numeric types first
这里我们以8位无符号整数来举例
Here we take 8-bit unsigned integer as an example
我们定义了一个数据类型
We define a data type
它的名字叫做MyUnsignedNumber
Its name is MyUnsignedNumber
它的类型是一个StorageValue
Its type is a StorageValue
那这个单值类型存储的
Then this single value type stores
类型是一个8位无符号的整数
the type which is an 8-bit unsigned integer
同样呢我们有一个可见的Get函数
Also we have a visible Get function
是my_unsigned_number
It is my_unsigned_number
这里我们又举了另外一个例子
Here we give another example
是一个有符号的8位整数
It is a signed 8-bit integer
同样的是一个storageValue类型
It is also a storageValue type
里面存储元素是i8
The storage element inside is i8
可以看到
We can see
这里我们给了第三个泛型参数
Here we give the third generic parameter
叫做ValueQuery
called ValueQuery
它表示的是我们是使用
It means that we are using
ValueQuery这种形式来
ValueQuery of this form
去读取链上存储单元
to read the storage unit on the chain.
如果不指定的话是默认的是OptionQuery
If it is not specified, the default is OptionQuery
也就是默认的话
That is, the default
如果没有值会返回一个Option
Returning an Option if there is no value
也就是None这样的一个值
That is, a value like None
那如果使用ValueQuarry的话
Then if you use ValueQuery
如果是没有值的话我们就会返回一个
If there is no value, we will return a
那么就会返回一个
then it will return a
所存储类型的一个默认值
a default value for the stored type
比如i8的话它的默认值就是0
For example, for i8, its default value is 0
对于单值类型一些常用的API有
Some commonly used APIs for single value types are
比如我们可以使用Put
For example, we can use Put
方法来更新链上的存储单元
method to update storage units on the chain
我们使用Get方法获取
We use the Get method to obtain
当前链上存储单元里面所存储的值
the value stored in the storage unit on the current chain
要用mutate来更新一个
To use mutate to update a
存储的值变成一个新的值
stored value to a new value
我们还可以使用q来删除
We can also use q to delete
当前存储单元里面已经存储的值
the value already stored in the current storage unit
这里我给到了一个链接
here i gave a link
是StorageValue的接口文档
It is the interface document of StorageValue
大家有兴趣的话可以看一下
If you are interested, you can take a look
那对于所存储的数
That for the stored number
值类型
value type
我们通常在区块链应用开发的时候
We usually use some security operations
要使用一些安全性的操作
in developing blockchain applications
来避免一些溢出性的错误
to avoid some overflow errors
比如会返回None类型的一些安全操作
For example, some security operations that return None type
包括checked_add checked_sub
include checked_add checked_sub
checked_multiply以及checked_divide
checked_multiply and checked_divide
我们以checked_add的为例
Let's take checked_add as an example
当我们相加之后的结果是溢出了
When the result of adding is overflow
那么我们会去返回一个错误信息
Then we will return an error message
从而我们可以很及时的去判断
Thus we can judge the wrong scene
错误的场景
in a timely manner
进而让我们的这这笔交易去失败
and let our deal fail
除了checked_*
except checked_*
这一类的返回results
This kind of safe operation
returning result
类型的安全操作之外
还有一类安全操作是会返回饱和值
Another type of safe operation is to return a saturation value
也就是溢出的时候返回最大值
That is, when overflow, returning the maximum value
这些操作包括saturating_add
These operations include saturating_add
saturating_sub等等
saturating_sub etc.
这里以saturating_add的为例我们对一个
Here we take saturating_add as an example for an
无符号的8位整数
unsigned 8-bit integer
加了一个很大的整数1万
Added a large integer 10,000
那很明显它超过了它的最大值
That's clearly over it's maximum
那么我们就会去饱和值就是最大值255
then we'll saturate the value to a maximum of 255
对于大整数类型
For large integer types
嗯和整数类型是很类似的
Well, it is very similar to the integer type
不过我们需要去在我们的代码里
But we need to go in our code
首先引入大整数类型的定义
First introduce the definition of large integer type
它是在sp_core里面
It is inside sp_core
这里
here
我们定义了一个大整数类型的名字
We define a large integer type with the name
叫my_big_integer
called my_big_integer
那它是一个StorageValue
then it is a StorageValue
的这样一个存储类型
Such a storage type of
里面存储的数据类型是U256
The data type stored in it is U256
同样的对于大整数也提供了一些
Similarly for large integers some
内置的安全性的操作的方法
methods of operation with built-in security are provided
比如checked_add overflow multiply
For example checked_add overflow multiply
这里也给到了接口文档的链接
Here is also a link to the interface documentation
对于布尔类型是很类似的
For boolean type is very similar
我们这里定义了一个存储单元
Here we define a storage unit
它的名字叫MyBool
Its name is MyBool
它是一个单值类型
it is a single value type
单值类型里面存储的类型是布尔类型
The type stored in the single value type is Boolean type
通常链上通过存储布尔类型
Usually on-chain by storing boolean type
来存储一些标志性的信息
To store some symbolic information
并且可以根据链上存储的标志性信息
And it can be based on the iconic information stored on the chain
在代码里进行逻辑判断
to make logical judgments in the code
同样的默认的是一个OptionQuery
The same default is an OptionQuery
对于ValueQuery的话它的默认值是false
For ValueQuery, its default value is false
在Substrate里面
Inside Substrate
不能直接使用Rust内置的vector
You cannot directly use Rust's built-in vector
集合类型
collection type
而是使用
Instead use
自定义的BoundedVec这样一个集合类型
custom BoundedVec such a collection type
可以看到
We can see
这行代码我们定义了一个type MyString
In this line of code we define a type MyString
然后它是一个StorageValue
Then it is a StorageValue
也就是单值类型
That is, single value type
它的值是
Its value is
BoundedVector是一个集合
BoundedVector which is a collection
那BoundedVector有两个范型参数
Then BoundedVector has two generic parameters
第一个是集合里面的数据类型
The first is the data type in the collection
这里是8位无符号整数
Here is the 8 bit unsigned integer
然后集合内的最大长度是100
Then the maximum length within the set is 100
然后它是一个ValueQuery
Then it is a ValueQuery
就是会返回一个默认值
it will return a default value
如果
if
存储项不存在的话
If the storage item does not exist
对于BoundedVector有这些常用的操作
There are these common operations for BoundedVector
比如try_push可以去添加一个元素
For example, try_push can add an element
remove可以去删除一个元素
remove can delete an element
iter可以去
iter can
遍历
traverse
这样的一个BoundedVector集合数据类型
such a BoundedVector collection data type
这里我们给出了Substrate的文档链接
Here we give the documentation link for Substrate
那对于BoundedVector它的默认值是0x00
The default value for BoundedVector is 0x00
是用ValueQuery这种形式
It is in the form of ValueQuery
接着我们来看一下
Let's take a look
定点小数Percent Permill
Fixed-point decimal Percent Permill
Perbill这样的一个类型定义
Perbill these types definitions
我们需要首先引入对应的类型
We need to first introduce the corresponding type
在sp_runtime里面
inside sp_runtime
这里我们定义了一个存储项
Here we define a storage item
它的名字叫MyPermill
Its name is MyPermill
它是一个单值类型
it is a single value type
存储的类型是Permill
The storage type is Permill
对于这种定点小数类型
For this fixed-point decimal type
Substrate内置了一些构造方法
Substrate has some built-in construction methods
比如我们可以使用Percent来构建一个
For example, we can use Percent to build a
包含百分之几这样的一个
Permill data containing
Permill的数据
a few percent
也可以使用from_parts
You can also use from_parts
to give a value to indicate
来给定一个值来表示是
100万分之几
Parts per million
比如我们这里可以给定1,000
For example, we can give 1,000 here
那我们如果value是1,000的话
Then if the value is 1,000,
那我们
then we
Permill::from_parts的话就是1,000/1,000,000
Permill::from_parts is 1,000/1,000,000
类似的我们还可以使用form_rational这种
Similarly, we can also use form_rational
给定分子p
given molecule p
和分母q这种机制来构造一个
and denominator q this mechanism to construct a
定点小数类型
Fixed-point decimal type
使用
When
Permill这种类型进行计算的时候
using Permill type to calculate
也有一些二进制操作
There are also some binary operations
比如是saturating_mul可以将两个
For example, saturating_mul can multiply two
Permill的数据类型进行相乘
Permill data types
我们也可以和一些
we can also multiply with some
整数类型直接进行相乘
Integer types directly
并且进行一些转换
and do some conversions
但是我们要格外
but we have to be extra
注意一些可能溢出的场景
aware of some possible overflow scenarios
这里我们也给到了Permill的定义
Here we also give the definition of Permill
里面有一些帮助性的方法
There are some helpful methods in it
大家可以去参考一下
You can refer to it
在Substrate开发过程中
During Substrate development
合理的使用API文档是特别关键的
Reasonable use of API documentation is particularly critical
因为现在
Because now
通常这些API
Usually these APIs
文档里面有非常多的描述性信息
There is a lot of descriptive information in the document
以及使用的例子
and examples of using
结合API文档以及
Combining API documentation and
现有的substrate内置的一些代码示例
Some code examples built into existing Substrate
we'll be fine to
我们就可以很好的去
理解和使用对应的
understand and use the corresponding
存储数据类型
storage data type
这里我们再看一个
Here we look at another
自定义的类型叫做moment
custom type which is called moment
表示我们的时间
showing our time
我们刚才讲到
we just talked about
它是在timestamp模块里面去定义的
It is defined in the timestamp module
当我们想使用
when we want to use
timestamp模块所定义的moment类型的时候
the moment type defined by the timestamp module
我们可以让我们的配置接口去
We can let our config interface to
继承自timestamp
inherit from the configuration interface
里面的配置接口
inside the timestamp.
这样我们的
so our
当前模块就可以拥有
current module can have
moment的这样一个类型定义
such a type definition of moment
这里我们定了一个存储单元叫做MyTime
Here we set a storage unit called MyTime
它的类型是一个单值类型
Its type is a single value type
它存储的数据是T::Moment
The data it stores is T::Moment
也就是来源于我们的
That is from our
Timestamp模块里面定义的这样moment类型
the moment type defined in the Timestamp module.
通常情况下
Usually
moment类型在实现的时候就是一个U64
the moment type is a U64 when it is implemented
这样的一个类型别名
A type alias like this
我们可以通过这种方式来获取
We can get time on chain
链上的时间
by this way.
通过调用pallet_timestamp模块下的
By calling the public exposed method get
公共暴露的方法get
under the pallet_timestamp module
来获取当前
to get the current
timestamp模块里面所存储的链上时间
on-chain time stored in the timestamp module
还有一类自定义的类型是
There is also a class of custom types that is
系统模块所提供的AccountId
AccountId provided by the system module
这里我们定义了一个存储单元类型
Here we define a storage unit type
叫做MyAccountId
called MyAccountId
然后它是一个单值类型
Then it is a single value type
它的存储数据是T::AccountId
Its storage data is T::AccountId
也就是由我们系统模块
That is, Provided by our system module
提供的这样一个关联类型
such an association type
AccountId
我们刚才也已经说过了
we just said
它是在系统模块里面定义
It is defined in the system module
并且通常是
and usually
用户私钥所对应的公匙信息
The public key information corresponding to the user's private key
系统模块还提供了一个帮助方法
The system module also provides a helper method
可以很好的从
which can get our AccountId
我们的交易发送方获取我们的AccountId
from our transaction sender
就是ensure_signed这样的一个帮助方法
It is a helper method like ensure_signed
对于有
For
存储复杂信息要求的这样的一些场景
some scenarios such as storage complex information requirements
我们可以使用结构体
We can use the structure
比如这里我们定了一个结构体是people
For example, here we set a structure that is people
它有两个属性一个是name
It has two attributes one is name
表示人的名字
that Indicates the person's name
age表示人的年龄
age means the age of the person
为了能够在链上存储这样一个结构体
To be able to store such a structure on-chain
我们需要让我们讲一个结构体实现
We need to know how does a struct implement
这些接口
these interfaces
我们是使用derive这种形式
We use the form of derive
去自动的帮我们生成
to automatically generate
对应的实现
corresponding realization for us
比如
for example
编解码所需要的encode的decode的实现
The implementation of decode required for encoding and decoding
以及默认值Default的实现
and the implementation of the default value Default
这里我们就可以定义
Here we can define
一个新的存储单元
a new storage unit
叫做MyStruct
called MyStruct
它是个单值类型
it is a single value type
里面存储的数据是People
The data stored in it is People
这样一个结构体
such a structure
那对于Enum类型
That for the Enum type
它和Struct是很类似的
It is very similar to Struct
只不过它需要手动的去实行
But the default interface
default接口
needs to be done manually.
没有办法通过derive这种形式去
There is no way to use this form of
派生出来
derive
这里我给出来一个Enum的例子
Here I give an example of Enum
有兴趣的话大家也可以看一下
If you are interested, you can also take a look
我们刚才已经看过了一些单值类型
We have just looked at some single value types
Substrate所支持的一些单值类型
Some single-value types supported by Substrate
现在我们来看一下
now let's see
如何构造简单的映射类型
How to construct a simple mapped type
也就是我们这里的StorageMap
That is our StorageMap here
它通常是用来保存键值对
It is usually used to store key-value pairs
那我们刚才提到的
what we just mentioned
单值类型都可以用作key
Single-value types can be used as keys
或者用作value来使用
or use it as value
这里我们定义了一个存储项叫做MyMap
Here we define a storage item called MyMap
它是一个StorageMap
It is a StorageMap
这样的一个映射类型
such a mapping type
那map里面的key是一个U8
The key in the map is a U8
值是我们系统模块定义的哈西类型
The value is the hash type defined by our system module
这里Blake2_128Concat是一个哈西算法
Here Blake2_128Concat is a hash algorithm
它是用来对我们的key进行哈西
It is used to hash our key
进而使用哈西后的结果作为一个
and then use the hashed result as a
Key-value数据库真正
key used for storage
存储的时候所用到的那个key
in the key-value database
那对应的key算法
The corresponding key algorithm
除了Blake2_128Concat之外
In addition to Blake2_128Concat
还有Twox64Concat Identity
There is also Twox64Concat Identity
以及对应的非Concat
and the corresponding non-Concat
这样的一个哈西算法
Such a hash algorithm
它们的区别是Blake2_128
Their difference is Blake2_128
是一个密码学安全的哈西算法
is a cryptographically secure hash algorithm
那Twox64的话它的速度会更快
Then Twox64 will be faster
但是它不是一个密码学安全的
But it is not a cryptographically secure
哈西算法
Hash algorithm
Identity通常是用在
Identity is usually used in
当我们的key本身已经是一个哈西的
When our key itself is already a Hash
结果的时候
result,
我们可以使用Identity来避免一些
We can use Identity to avoid some
额外的不必要的计算
additional unnecessary calculations
对于storage map这样的一个类型
For a type like storage map
我们有这样一些常用的API
We have some commonly used APIs like this
比如我们可以通过insert方法去
For example, we can use the insert method to
插入一个键值
insert a key
我们可以通过get
We can get
来给定一个key来获取对应的
to give a key to get the corresponding
映射里面的值
value in the map
我们还可以通过remove方法给定key
We can also give the key through the remove method
来删除某一个元素
to delete an element
对于修改和覆盖
For modification and overwriting
元素我们可以使用insert进行覆盖
elements, we can use insert to cover
或者使用mutate来更改一个原有的值
or use mutate to change an existing value
更新成一个新的值
update to a new value
这里我们
here
给到了一个StorageMap的接口文档
a StorageMap interface document is given
还有一点需要说的是
one more thing to say
StorageMap实现了
StorageMap implements
Iterable StorageMap这样一个接口
Iterable StorageMap such an interface
可以用来迭代我们
can be used to iterate
StorageMap里面所有的key value
all key values ​​in StorageMap
但是在迭代的时候我们要尤其
But when iterating we have to especially
格外注意
pay extra attention
不能让链上迭代的时间
The time to iterate on the chain cannot be allowed
超过我们区块的生成时间
exceeding the generation time of our block
这样的话
In this case
就有可能导致我们不能正常的出块
It may cause us to fail to produce blocks normally
所以在迭代的时候要格外的小心
So be extra careful when iterating
接着我们就可以看一下
Then we can see
双键形式类型StorageDoubleMap
Double key form type StorageDoubleMap
那顾名思义它就是用了两个key来索引
As the name implies, it uses two keys to index
一个value
a value
它的好处是你可以快速的去删除
Its advantage is that you can quickly delete
第一个key也就是key1所对应的任意记录
The first key is any record corresponding to key1
也可以快速遍历key1所对应的所有记录
You can also quickly traverse all records corresponding to key1
这里我们定义了一个存储项叫做
Here we define a storage item called
MyDoubleMap
它是StorageDoubleMap这样一个类型
It is a type of StorageDoubleMap
它的key1是AccountId
Its key1 is AccountId
key2是U32 所存储的值是一个哈西
key2 is U32 and the stored value is a Hash
这里为大家简单起见
Here for the sake of simplicity
我们都是使用Blake2_128
We are all using Blake2_128
这样的一个哈西算法
such a hash algorithm
在正式的代码中的话
In formal code
我们通常是要根据上下文
We usually want to use the context
根据key的类型以及
according to the type of key and
它的输入来源
its input source
来去选择一个合适的哈西算法
to choose a suitable hash algorithm
通常情况下是当
Usually
输入是由用户控制的时候
When the input is controlled by the user
我们需要用一个密码学安全的
We need to use a cryptographically secure
哈西算法
Hash algorithm
比如是Blake2_128
For example, Blake2_128
但是如果这个数据本身是由
But if this data itself is composed of
系统所控制
controlled by the system
能够保证它不会被任意的输入
which can guarantee that it will not be arbitrarily entered
那我们就可以使用更快的
Then we can use the faster
Twox64这样一个哈西算法
Hash algorithm such as Twox64
刚才我们已提到过了
We just mentioned
如果这个key本身已经是一个
If we can already guarantee that
我们已经可以保证它是一个
the key itself is
密码学安全的输出或者一个
a cryptographically secure output or a
哈西结果的输出
output of the hash result
我们就可以直接使用
we can directly use
identity这种机制
identity mechanism
来避免额外的哈西计算的开销
to avoid the overhead of additional hash calculations
对于
for
StorageDoubleMap这种类型我们有这些API
StorageDoubleMap this type we have these APIs
我们可以使用insert的方法来插入key1
We can use the insert method to insert key1
key2以及对应的value值
key2 and the corresponding value
然后我们还可以通过Get的方法给定key1
Then we can also give key1 through the method of Get
key2来获取对应的元素值
key2 to get the corresponding element value
使用remove方法来删除key1
Use the remove method to delete
key2对应的元素值
The elements values corresponding to key 1 and key2
那我们刚才提到了
then we just mentioned
StorageDoubleMap的一个好处是
One benefit of StorageDoubleMap is that
可以快速的删除key1所有的元素
it can quickly delete all elements of key1
那这样的API就是remove prefix
Then such an API is remove prefix
这里我也给出了StorageDoubleMap的API文档
Here I also give the API documentation for StorageDoubleMap
大家有时间的话一定要读
If you have time, you can
一读
read it
和StorageMap很类似
Similar to StorageMap
StorageDoubleMap也实现了一个叫做
StorageDoubleMap also implements a method called
iterable storage double map这样的一个接口
an interface like iterable storage double map
能够对我们的双键映射类型里面
which is able to traverse all elements in
所有的元素进行一个迭代
the double bond type
同样的
same
我们在迭代的时候要格外的小心
We have to be extra careful when iterating
不能让迭代的时间
we can't let iteration time
超过我们的区块实证时间
exceed our block verification time
接着我们来看一下存储的初始化
Next, let's look at the initialization of the storage
那通常在创始区块的时候
usually at the time of the genesis block
我们对于某些模块要初始化一些
For some modules we want to initialize some
需要的数据
required data
那我们是定义这样的一个GenesisConfig
Then we define such a GenesisConfig
这样的一个结构体
such a structure
那这样的一个需要的数据
Then such a required data
它的名字就是value
its name is value
它数据类型是一个U8类型
Its data type is a U8 type
这是我们以这样一个简单的类型举例
Here is our example with such a simple type
那我们还需要使用genesis_config
Then we also need to use genesis_config
这样一个宏来表示
Such a macro to represent
这个结构体是需要在创始
that this structure is needed in the initial
区块里面进行配置的
configured in the block
配置是通常发生在Chainspec文件里面
Configuration usually happens in the Chainspec file
我们还需要去实现一个Default接口
We also need to implement a Default interface
这里它Default值很简单
Here its Default value is very simple
就是我们
it's
U8这样一个数值类型的Default值
Default value of a numeric type such as U8
也就是0
That is 0
我们还需要去
we still need to
实现genesis_build这样的一个接口
implement an interface like genesis_build
当我们在初始化的时候对我们的
When we initialize our
chainspec里面的初始化的值进行
value in the chainspec, we need to do
一系列操作
series of operations
来更新我们链上的存储单元
to update storage units on our chain
比如这里我们在build的时候
For example, here when we are building
我们将
we will
Chainspec里面所配置的
take out the initial value
初始值value拿出来
configured in Chainspec
然后放在我们
then put in
MyValue这样的一个存储项里面
a storage item like MyValue
大家可以去参考Substrate内置的
You can refer to Substrate's built-in
Sudo模块里面的一些实现
implementations in the Sudo module
它里面定义了一个
It defines a
很简单的初始化的配置
Very simple initial configuration
这里我还想给大家
Here I also want to share with you
分享一些在
some
Substrate进行链上存储设计的时候
best practices
一些最佳实践
when Substrate is designing on-chain storage
我们刚才已经提到过了
we just mentioned
链上的存储资源是相对比较昂贵的
On-chain storage resources are relatively expensive
因为它会在
because it will
成千上万个节点里面进行一个备份
make a backup in thousands of nodes
所以通常情况下我们要把一些
So usually we'll take some
源信息
source information
或者说大文件的信息要存储在一个
In other words, the information of large files should be stored by a
更有利的去中心的存储机制
more favorable decentralized storage mechanism
或者中心化存储机制里面
or in the centralized storage mechanism
链上只存储一个小的哈西值
Only a small hash value is stored on the chain
还有一个就是
Another one is
当我们有集合类的数据类型的时候
When we have a data type of collection class
我们要去
we are going to
设置这样一个集合所
set up the maximum capacity that can be carried
能承载的最大容量
in such a collection
来保证他不会占用过多的空间
to make sure it doesn't take up too much space
另外一个比较好的实践是
Another good practice is that
我们尽可能的在
we try our best to
开始的时候
check all possible error scenarios
校验所有的可能错误的场景
at the beginning
那校验完成之后
After the verification is completed
我们再进行我们存储项的更新操作
Let's update our storage items again
也就是verify first write last
That is verify first write last
那在substrate的最新的版本也就是
The latest version in substrate is
frame V2新的语法里面
inside the new syntax of frame V2
提供了一个transactional这样一个宏
It provides a transactional such a macro
它可以保证我们
it guarantees us
可调函数的这样的一个
atomic operations
原子化的操作
of callable functions
也就是说当有错误发生的时候
That is, when an error occurs
我们可以保证
we can guarantee that
之前对存储项的操作会去回滚
previous operations on storage items will be rolled back
尽管我们有这样的一个原子性操作的
Although we have such an atomic operation
宏那我们还是希望大家能够在
Macro, we still hope that when operating
操作的时候
everyone can
先去对错误的场景进行的校验
check the wrong scene first
然后最终再去更新
and finally update
另外一些其他的点
some other points
我想分享的是
what i want to share is
我们可以在
we can
对存储单元使用pub关键字
use the pub keyword for storage units
来设置这样的
to set the
存储单元对不同模块的可见范围
visibility range of storage unit to different modules
然后我们的ValueQuery
Then our ValueQuery
也可以设置一些自定义的默认值
It is also possible to set some custom default values
这里我给到了一个例子
Here I give an example
那当大家对某些存储的API
Then when everyone doesn't know certain storage APIs
不是很了解的时候
that well
我们可以去参考
we can refer to
substrate frame目录下的不同的pallets
different pallets under the substrate frame directory
来查找一些最新的使用方法
to find some of the newest ways to use
还可以结合API文档
We can also read API documentations
比如这里的palettes::storage是宏的
For example, palettes::storage here is a macro
接口文档以及我们刚才
documentation and what we just
列出的不同的存储数据类型
list the different storage data types
它的API文档
its API documentation
今天课程内容到这里就结束了
Today's course content is over here
谢谢大家
thank you all